[Music]
ah o
hello welcome good day good evening
everybody wherever you are I hope you're
doing well and welcome to the latest
episode epis of the ask abijit show this
is a live chat episode which means you
will ask me questions in the live chat I
and I will take questions only from the
YouTube live chat as always let me see
who is who all is there who all is in
attendance let's see I can see om I can
see anjel promode from rajot Hello
WV Gil chandarana Amaya tpal somia nand
gizor abishek tripati Pros random skull
hello shamik Roy Gort walmort karat jri
omik hello gorov Atara pujari takur pan
Kumar Singh B miir Tali Raj choa Namaste
panetti red Hello Shri balam Putin ram
ram Hur Krishna Shri Ram chandraa namaha
Atul ragir solanki suit mukarji
strangely proton
Nacho abinav Yash tiari geopolitical dub
hello B Panda Dave tapan D tapan sagya
Das Adel kza from South Africa hello WRV
Kumar kanesh
shamik uh who else Nero sukram hello new
member welcome thank you so much Matrix
atar sidhant Vladimir
abijit and aant d kamat and lots of
other people so I will not
I'll stop there thank you so much all of
you for being on this live stream and
let us get on with the questions let me
greet some more people subit Sonia Sinha
Dr J Shankar hello anant pal minini parb
Malik say Joy
Maharashtra Kumar keska crazy brain
hello M Ling yo and everybody else okay
okay okay let's get going with the
questions lots of stuff happening in the
world
in the world of uh well there's not a
lot of stuff happening in the world of
history because it's happening in the
world of geopolitics and geopolitics is
how history is made so there's not a lot
happening in the field of history but
lots of geopolitical developments lots
of lots of things happening in the world
of science as well so let's see what all
you ask and I'm going to this episode
will be driven by you and the questions
you ask in the live chat okay well let's
go Atul says your views on the new
nalanda campus inauguration My Views
what are My Views My Views is that it's
a new University that's been inaugurated
and it has been given the name of
nalanda University does it mean that it
has the same standards in the same
values as the original Nanda it doesn't
mean that uh I don't know for sure
because I've not looked into the
curriculum their their their faculty the
courses they are offering and so on but
it's going to be in line with the
current Indian education system which is
a continuation of the 19th century
colonial education system I don't expect
there to be any change any any any any
diversion from the path of the modern
Colonial Indian education system it's
going to be along the same lines so I
don't see it as some kind of game
changer that will change and transform
the world or something and turn India
overnight into a visha guru no
I think uh hopefully it it can do
something good it all depends on what
the government does with this
institution if they have the same
structure and the same curriculum and
the same system uh ba ma BSC MSC
PhD the same uh promotion system you're
promoted on the basis of
seniority and if you have the same
system wherein the non non-academic
staff controls the budget and overall
the direction and the academic staff is
reduced to just playing politics then
what's the point of having of of calling
something nalanda nalanda had a certain
standard the greatest University of the
ancient world right one of the greatest
universities of the ancient world so
just calling some just pasting a sticker
on on something which is the old stuff
will not make it better so I am not
really excited about this and if you
look at the campus if you look at the
design of the campus the architecture
the colors it is ghastly it is
absolutely
ghastly so yeah nothing that excites me
really
yeah okay let's see other questions
let's let's take some interesting
questions shall we please ask me
interesting questions guys girls ladies
gentlemen's boys girls Etc okay Malik
said says is it possible to become a
multi-millionaire coming from a lower
middle class background of course it is
it is easier in some countries it is
more difficult in some countries if you
are in the US it's way easier look at
Steve Jobs he was an orphan he was
adopted by a bunch of by by middle-
class couple his father was from Syria
Mr jandali his mother was American white
lady and because his father was a Muslim
and the the L's parents did not like
that that's why they had to give the boy
the child up for adoption after he was
born and the same thing happened to his
sister so he was an orphan he was given
up for adoption he did not know who his
parents were until he was in his 20s or
30s when he discovered it and he was
from middle class background and he
dropped out of what some which
university was that one of the big
universities but look at what he did
what he achieved
um there are so many other examples in
the US when it comes to India it's I
think much harder to become a
multi-millionaire billionaire if you
come from a middle lower middle class
background but look at the big stories
everybody when you talk about
Millionaires and billionaires first of
all you have the Millionaires and
billionaires from from the from the 20th
century first half of the 20th century
those were the people who made their
money because of because of their
Cooperative attitude towards the British
and after 1947 their children inherited
the money and they were able to take
that forward the Tas the beras and so on
the whatever right Tata bla these names
are very very much old money which means
British money British era money and and
if you became a millionaire or a
billionaire during that time it was only
because you cooperated and collaborated
with the British and aided them in their
business of occupation and extraction
out of India so that's the old money
that we talk
about uh and then there are there's a
case of of people of people like the
ambanis and the Adan Adan the adanes
came first and later the adanes right
later Mr adani so these so when it comes
to Mr duai Amani Mr goam adani I think
they came from very humble background
backgrounds right and they did so much
so it's much harder if you were in India
today it may be easier today you see
lots of success stories you see lots of
unicorns coming up lots of these
Founders are from proper middle class
backgrounds so you need to understand
the system you need to understand
business you need to understand the
problems that uh underly the Indian
system how to game not game the system
but how to navigate through the system
because there are problems that you
would not find in other more developed
countries that you face in India there
are certain let's say additional taxes
in certain cases and all kinds of stuff
right overall it's much harder to do
business in India just starting a
business it takes God knows how many
days right you can start a business in
two two to four hours in in a western
country over here it takes W so it's
harder in India but it is possible you
just have to find a way and you need to
have the right business ideas you need
to have the right uh business what's a
business Society has problems find a way
to solve the problem deliver the
solution at scale and then Society will
reward you for that with money that's a
business so it's possible but it's
harder in India
WRV 1313 says many International media
outlets and Wikipedia say that India has
lost 2,000 kilometers of land to China
after the 2020 border fights is that
true okay first of all I don't know how
many times I to say this okay I'm sure
you knew look Wikipedia is not a
reliable source of information Rel
Wikipedia is biased when it comes to
various articles about India whether
it's history or whatever it's going to
be seriously seriously biased in against
India Wikipedia is hinduphobic Wikipedia
is indo phobic okay so when it comes to
articles on science or articles about
other countries Etc articles about the
Roman Empire Greek Empire you'll be
you'll find you'll find reasonably good
information on Wikipedia when it comes
to articles about India it's it's you'll
see serious biases so first of all there
is that then when it comes to
International media Outlets you mean the
englishspeaking media right the media
that communicates in English you're
talking about the BBC the CNN or you may
be talking about certain Indian Outlets
that also published in
English once again there's agendas there
so I don't know what the real truth is I
have seen personally no evidence that
India has lost 2,000 I I'm sure you
talking about square kilometers here
square kilometers are you talking about
a linear what dimension are you talking
about are you talking about kilometers
or square kilometers let's assume you're
talking about square kilometers because
land is measured the area is measured in
square kilometers to ,000 square
kilometers is a
large
area Okay so that's not small area and I
don't I don't I doubt it very much if
India has lost that much
territory but uh what you can do is you
can look at late the latest satellite
images and all that which you will have
to purchase obviously Google Maps is in
the latest imagery and then you can see
where the Chinese positions are and the
Indian positions are and you will find
that I I've been doing that over time I
don't see any significant difference so
I don't think this is true but you can
do your own due diligence instead of
asking people for opinions it is always
better to try and Source the information
for oneself so I don't think it is true
I don't think there's been significant
uh change in the status quo when it
comes to the undemarcated Border there's
always some give and take some push back
and all that because the border is
undemarcated there is an official border
that India claims there is an of I don't
know what border China even
claims and China obviously is in illegal
possession of Tibet that's the main
issue and maybe we will reopen that
issue so as of now um I don't think
there's been been any major
change dndd mode says please say
something about
nalism nalism what is nalism it's it's a
it's an outlook on life that says that
everything is
futile life is futile existence is
futile doing work is futile hoping is
futile it's a very
dark sad miserable ideology not ideology
philosophy it's a philosophical school
of thought that's what nalism is
everything is pointless why are we doing
this just sit down and die lie down
close your eyes stop working give up
that essentially is nalism the way I as
far as I know I have never never really
studied nalism it has never appealed to
me but it's a very negative and very
pessimistic
uh school of thought philosophical
school of thought so that's the little I
know about it nothing that interests me
too much I'm a very optimistic person
okay so yeah not for
me
okay Arijit banerji says will the US
give the power of the British British
Empire to India due to fear of China
which was given to the US by
UK that's a power is not something
that's in a box okay here take some of
it and okay three spoonfuls of power
that's not how it works and when it
comes to power you never share power you
never never never never sh share power
and you never become a superpower
without understanding that you don't
share power the us is going to share
nothing with India nothing India is
merely a tool with limited utility for
the US and it's up to India whether we
allow them to use us as a tool or not if
we push back against their plans to use
us us as a tool they're going to hurt
India they'll strive to hurt India so in
the US is going to give no power to
India stop living in la la land if if
any of you are the us is going to the US
is nobody's friend it's not a friend of
the UK or Australia or newand or Canada
or any English speaking country it's not
a friend of this religion or that
religion it's not a friend of this
nation or that Nation the only interests
that the US serves is its own interests
it's at the expense of everybody else
when it serves them when it suits them
they'll be friends with everybody and
make you feel like yeah you know we are
your friends but the moment they need
something they're going to go for it
whether it hurts you or not doesn't
matter so the US is giving no power to
India the US is not India's friend or
anybody's friend and India and the
future coming years are going to be
pretty tough not just for India for the
rest of the world and when it comes to
China the Chinese you know it's their
choice whether they want India on this
side or that side India doesn't have any
desire to be an enemy of China the
Chinese have forced India to take uh you
know certain steps out of the need for
self-preservation that's it so it's
entirely China's fault if there is if
there are problems between India and
China and the resolution lies in the
hands of China itself so yeah there we
have
it do you think China is a communist or
capitalist country it's a capitalist
country it's an imperialistic country
it's an Empire it's not a nation it's an
Empire
okay Paran poel says why did India turn
Nepal into a republic Nation it's an
interesting question Nepal was the last
surviving Hindu Nation on the planet
Nepal was a Raj Tantra a monarchy they
had a Hindu king a Hindu Dynasty and in
in the 1990s there was this maest
Uprising and it has re emerged in the
past decade or so that the then
government of India run by certain
political parties was in support of this
maist Insurgency and then all the maist
leaders were essentially jnu educated
Elites right jnu is the snake pit of the
maoist and leftist and Marxist isn't it
jnu javal Neu University in
Delhi and most Indian universities are
like that when it comes to the sociology
Department Humanities departments
they're all snake pits of the leftist
Marxist maoists so these nepales
individuals were all educated in these
universities and they were at the
Forefront of this let's say Insurgency
against the nepales government in
monarchy and apparently it was aided and
ab beted by the then government of India
which was controlled by certain specific
uh political parties and the result was
that the nepales monarchy was destroyed
the last surviving Hindu Kingdom on the
planet was turned into a secular nation
and now they have a gigantic
fat constitution of some kind yes and
then their political Elite is all
leftists marxists maoists who are more
or less either overtly or covertly Hindu
phobes and they are overly pro-china and
overly anti-india most of them so yes
India certain the the then government of
India run by those who led by certain
political parties was behind this
disaster and we know that the nepales
royal family was massacred and it is
alleged that Prince dender was behind
this I don't buy that I don't buy that
at all so yeah and I think there is
demand I mean there is this movement
this growing movement in Nepal to to
return to a Hindu Raj Tantra status well
I can only say that I wish the people of
Nepal the very best there's lots of
problems that Nepal has facing first of
all it is sandwich between a very
dangerous country China and a country
that is a secular Nation
India secondly uh it is a low income
Nation as of right now the major source
of income is tourism of course as we
know and there are these uh very very
nefarious elements that have been in uh
operating in Nepal since especially
since the earthquake happened a few
years ago there are large scale
Christian conversions happening in Nepal
when people are poor they will convert
for for a few meals you know or for
certain very small favors inducements so
large scale Christian conversions
happening in Nepal there are other
conversions also happening in Nepal
other other other flavors of
abrahamism
and and yeah that's a situation so there
there is this movement this growing
movement that I hear of that that there
is a section of Nepali society that
would like to return to Hindu Raj Tantra
status Hindu monarchy but let's see how
how far it can be can be successful so
yeah I would say that uh I simply wish
the people of Nepal the very
best
okay um let us see what else we
have sesh says how can one join politics
in India can one join without any
political background and be what can be
the road map
look okay look I am not in politics okay
um so I may probably not be the best
person to ask this but the best way to
join politics in India is simply walk
into your favorite political parties
local office and say that I want to
become a member then they will give you
membership Maybe they'll do some
background check I suppose and then you
get into this and depending on your
qualities your talents your aptitudes
they'll give you various roles and
they'll see how you perform and whether
you good at organization whether you're
good at
uh field work or or whatever they'll
give you specific positions based on
that because the political parties
always seek talent I suppose not all
political parties seek Talent by the way
but I suppose some we know of some
political parties that do seek talent
that that do reward and appreciate
Talent so depending on what your fav
favorite political party is you it may
be easier or less easy to advance
depending on your skills and your
aptitude and your talents so I say
that's how you do it that's how you get
into politics now how do you rise it
entirely depends on your aptitude your
talent your leadership qualities
organizational
qualities um hopefully patriotism in
some political parties patriotism is
actually valued some May in some
political parties allegedly it is not
that much valued so it depends depends
depends but yeah that's generally how
you do it you don't become foreign
minister or home minister after three
years in politics it's a long it's it's
a lifelong career so yeah I would say
that's how we do
it sain sha says your views on Hindus
destroying gen temples uh I've heard of
the of the Multiverse Theory man worlds
Theory so there are multiple parallel
universes that exist at the same time
it's a it's it's not Theory it's a
hypothesis it's one of the
interpretations of quantum mechanics
many world's interpretation so according
to this interpretation I mean if this
interpretation is true then in some
parallel universe Hindus may be
destroying Jane temples in the universe
that we inhabit it doesn't happen and it
has never happened in the past and it
won't happen in the future so these are
my
views
um okay what else what else else what
else what
else uh Rahul Mahajan says do you think
that the Modi 3.0
government can or will take any tough
decisions especially now as it's now a
coalition government I think Mr Modi
will have
to take some tough decisions because s
sometimes decisions you're forced into a
situation where you have to take a tough
decision so in some cases you're forced
into it despite you not wanting to do
that secondly there are some situations
where you simply have to do it whether
you being forced into it or not so
sometimes you're not forced into doing
anything but you have to do it or you
want to do it so why would the Modi
government want to take certain tough
decisions well first of all it is clear
that the people aren't very happy with
the Modi
government they did not give Mr Mod's
party the BJP a full majority this time
the people of India the people have
spoken janta janardan has spoken right
like Mr Modi says
so it's the first time in Mr Mod's
entire political career that he has
faced the situation that he has not won
an absolute majority so that is feedback
from the people to Mr Modi and to the
BJP and if they continue the status quo
and if they don't bring in any
significant
reforms by they will do a post morm and
understand try to understand why the
people have reacted in this manner
they've given the NDA a majority but not
the the BJP right so it's it's it's
feedback so clearly the people people
expected certain things that have not
happened and and clearly also it may be
true that the people expected did not
expect some things which have happened
so there's going to be a need for
significant course correction and if it
if if the status quo continues just the
way it is today until 2029 then it's
possible that the BJP and the NDA
overall may lose the majority so certain
sign significant actions will need to be
taken strong
actions tough decisions without
that political survival may not be
possible 2029 onwards or maybe even
before that so on the one hand because
of the election results and what the
people have told through the election
results it is clear that there is a need
for course correction at various levels
and various things which will require
tough decisions
whether it is in the economic policy
whether it is in delivery of services
whether it is in culture whether it's
civilizational issues other
issues whatever it is they will have to
take some T tough
decisions when it comes to certain
geopolitical things India may find
itself in situations where it doesn't
want to be and you will have to take
tough decisions what's happening in
Manipur is a good example so do we allow
the Americans to get away with whatever
they're doing
in case some of you don't know it's a
geopolitical situation it's not a Law
and Order issue so do we allow the
Americans to get away with what they are
trying to do or do we actually push back
and what's the pros and cons of that so
I think we going to see many tough decis
decisions in the next five
years and uh I I believe that Mr Modi
and his government had prepared a 100
day plan in which significant uh
steps will be taken significant reforms
or whatever will happen well that was
assuming there was a full majority which
did not happen so let's see what happens
now but I think overall they will have
to take dough decisions if they want
political survival and if they want to
win the next
election Kumar kanishka says how did the
first living cell come into existence
did it all start from protein molecules
or a meteor brought from brought the
first living cell can research on first
living cells provide answers well we
don't know when the first of we don't
know when the first living cells came
into existence the oldest evidence we
have points to life emerging at least
2.77 or 2.8 billion years before today
maybe 3.8 billion years before today I'm
not sure what the exact dating is the
thing about the first cells is that they
don't leave behind fossil traces because
they they have no hard structures in
them right no bones or no shells or
anything it's just microscopic cells so
we don't know for sure when the first
cells emerged when they came into
existence whatever the fossil record
says it would have been before that so
we don't know what the first cells
looked like what they were like what was
the structure whether they had DNA
whether they had nuclei whe they had
various organel like bodies
mitochondria blah blah blah we don't
know anything about that so in the
absence of evidence we can't we can't
provide answers so yeah that is one of
the Mysteries in biology we don't know
how life emerged on Earth
we know that like you're referring to
meteorites meteorites have been found
that contain amino acids and and amino
acids are the building blocks of
proteins which are the building blocks
of life so there seems to be some kind
of circumstantial evidence that
indicates that perhaps something
possibly may have come from space
Perhaps it is by no means any conclusive
evidence there is research that some
scientists some biologists Etc are doing
on this matter there are there's a field
called astrobiology which kind of looks
into this and so on but we don't have
the answers right now and when you have
a big mystery in science and you have a
big open field with lots of unanswered
questions that's that tells you that
that's a very interesting fascinating
field and that's a field where you can
do a lot of research so that's what I
can
say Summit statement says how do you
view the relations between the
anglosphere countries are they United in
every way or is it just like our
relations
with your country or Nepal oh you you
should from
Nepal what are the relations between
India and Nepal the relations okay you
have a political class that is pro-china
anti- India you have a political class
that is a yes anti- India they are they
are leftist Marxist Communists maoists
whatever we want to call them aligned
with China they don't like India and
they have created situation in Nepal
where if you want to be patriotic you to
show an anti-india tendency plus they
are hinduphobic they're allowing large
scale Christian conversions in your
country and so on so that is where Nepal
is and the relations with between Nepal
India are not very good apparently the
there is even some kind of question
about territorial boundaries and all
which all of this happened after the
1990s governments of India one specific
government which was run by one specific
political party it's after they
destroyed the Hindu monarchy in Nepal
and now everybody is like this not
everybody there are lots of people who
are kind of anti- indan in Nepal I'm
sure not all so relations aren't what
they should be between two Nations that
are the same people same
culture but that's where we are now then
the question is what's the relationship
between the anglosphere countries look
the anglosphere you to understand see
you don't look at it from the
perspective of geopolitics only or
international relations only you to
understand the history the history of
the Anglo people the Anglo-Saxon people
what kind of society do they come from
what kind of culture do they come from
the society in the anglosphere see the
anglosphere countries their people
originate from England right and which
are the anglosphere countries it's the
US of of course an artificial
Nation you have Canada another
artificial Nation you have Australia
another artificial Nation you have New
Zealand another artificial nation and
you have the mothership this tiny little
island called which is part of an island
called England so the US is an
artificial Nation created out of settler
colonialism and the theft of territory
of from the natives same goes for Canada
Australia New Zealand and England is the
mother mother country what's the
relationship like they all have one
dominant language in culture which is
the English language and the Anglo-Saxon
culture
things are changing in the US of
course um so historically the UK was the
dominant Force dominant power the UK
came into prominence in the last 400 or
so years after the uh golden age that
was precipitated by the coming to power
of
uh
Elizabeth was it Victoria Victorian
age who was Henry VII's daughter
who was Henry VI E's
daughter I'm not talking about Bloody
Mary I'm talking about uh I am talking
about Elizabeth so Elizabeth Elizabethan
age was the Golden Age of England which
precipitated a significant change in the
fortunes of England and they became this
giant even though it's a tiny Island
they became this giant powerful
superpower like Nation they conquered a
significant portion of the world and
they settled in lots of countes lotss of
territories that were not theirs today
the power lies resides in Washington
DC the center the the center of power
moved from London to Washington about 70
or so years ago so today the center of
power is the is the US it's Washington
Maryland you could say and from there
they control the whole world essentially
they do control much of the world and
when it comes to the relationship
between the US and Canada us and England
us and Australia us and New Zealand the
Americans essentially own the other
nations they won't let people understand
or realize this but they essentially own
these nations you can see it in that
matter master in vasal kind of
relationship and Australia I mean if it
if you look at Australia you have
permanent US military presence there
Australia is almost like a US
Corporation us owned Corporation
Canada it does whatever the Americans
tell them to do there's no way the
Canadians will ever go against the US
even put one foot out of
order so that is the deal and the
culture is a feudal culture if you look
at the over overall historical
Anglo-Saxon culture it's a feudal
culture it's a it's a culture dominated
by a certain it's a with a there's a
class system that has always existed in
this culture you have the monarchy then
you had the aristocracy which was the
nobility then you had the knights and
the the fighting folk and then you had
the peasants The
Peasants and of course you had the
clergy so that's why you needed the the
separation of church and state so the
majority of the population was the was
the peasantry The Peasants the oppressed
downtrodden peasants and they typically
had no rights the all land belonged to
the king or the crown and uh sometimes s
Nobles would hold the this various
parcel Parcels of land instead of the
crown on behalf of the crown and there
would be churches and monasteries that
also held significant portions of land
and some of up to certain time they used
to collect the revenues of that land and
so on until Henry Henry the E changed
everything the dissolution of the
monasteries happened so it's a very
feudal kind of structure historically
and that is deeply ingrained in the
psyche whether you realize it or not not
so when you have the US ruling over all
the other nations for them it's just the
natural order of things and they they
their politicians just understand that's
that's the world that's the way the
world works so overall that's the
relationship between the anglosphere
countries the Americans Dominate and own
essentially the other countries Master
vasal
relationship okay D Kad says can anyone
start their own country by Rec cling
land in the middle of a world ocean
that's not within any other country's
territorial Waters I suppose you could
but how do you do it it takes tremendous
amounts of money resources energy Etc to
reclaim even one square foot of land
anywhere in the
ocean so yeah
Tech but do you have the wherewithall to
defend it that's the question so it's
it's it's easier said than
done but I suppose you could try and do
it if you had the means for
that okay let's take some more
questions uh what else do we
have wire scientist says how can India
leverage Quantum Computing to gain a
competitive advantage in cyber security
and Technical technological
Innovation well first of all you need to
have the technology is anybody in India
working on Quantum Computing do we have
any I I I I hear that the Indian
government a few years ago had allocated
a Meely amount of money for research in
Quantum Technologies I'm not sure what's
happened whether they whether they built
prototype quantum computer if somebody's
building it who is building it who's
developing it who's doing research so
first of all you need to have multiple
places where research is being done not
just one place multiple places and they
all compete with with each other each
other in a collaborative way that's what
needs to happen first of all okay once
you have that then you will make
progress and depending on how much
funding is available and how much
technologically advanced you are you
will make progress at a certain
speed so how can India leverage
Computing first of all India needs to
have multiple centers where Quantum
Computing research is being done as far
as I'm aware and I'm usually aware of
things as far as I'm aware I'm aware we
are not doing that we have shouted some
slogans and we have made some
announcements but I don't know what's
happened after that so you want to have
so how do we do it first of all you you
decide that these five universities or
these 10 universities will be allocated
this much money each you appoint the
right people and you create institutes
where Quantum Computing research is done
then these let's say five or 10
universities compete among each other
for in building quantum computer then
you see how powerful the first quantum
computer is whenever you're able to
build one are you able to achieve super
position and all that and then are you
able to manipulate how many cubits do
you
have at at one given time you know how
many cubits are you able to have
persistent in your in your quantum
computer are you able to manipulate them
what means are you using to manipulate
them and to do calculations it's going
to take 5 10 years to reach a certain
stage in that then when do you reach
what the Google folks called Quantum
Supremacy so it's a long process you do
that you then you're going to make some
progress I don't think India has even
started as far as we know do we have a
single quantum computer in India we
don't have it so if you want to do this
if you don't want to be left behind in
the Stone Age when the whole world is
going ahead then this is how you have to
do it so India I have been saying this
I've been crying myself horse about this
for years that India needs to invest in
education India needs to reform the
education system India needs to focus on
sence and Technology lots of things need
to be done otherwise India will become a
puppet and a slave of other nations and
a simple follower instead of being a
leader forget about being a visha guru
we will become a visha
Ki uh so that that's how you would do it
I'm giving you a very rough high high
level overview you have to invest in
research in research centers you need to
hire the right people you to identify
and promote the right people not people
who are good at politics people who are
actually passionate about research and
really talented there are plenty of such
people in India but the system is rotten
the academic system is absolutely
garbage it is absolutely
rotten it is what it is I'm just telling
you the plain truth but yeah it's
certainly possible it certainly is
possible if you put the right people in
charge if you put the right amount of
resources if you put if you allocate the
right amount of funding and you give the
right amount of time it won't happen
next week if you start once you start
it's certainly possible
okay Karan nwat says what's better
making a career in data science versus a
career in mathematics is doing a PhD
from Top institutes in India worth it
look it it it all depends on what your
objective in life is do you want to
spend your life sitting in a room and
doing obscure research that 99.99% of
the world won't
read if that's your objective then you
can do a PhD from a top insute in India
and you can draw a decent salary if
you're lucky enough to get a job in a
top Institute and then you can spend
your life doing research and teaching
classes if that's your objective in life
some people are perfectly happy with
that for some people it's their dream
job to not gr get a great salary a
decent salary just to you know get by
and to have a research position in a top
university in India or maybe in the
world teach classes and do your research
that's that's many people's dream some
some people's dream not many people but
most people want to make money and have
a good life if you want to have lots of
money and a great life and lots of
options in life then you are better off
doing pursuing data science because data
science is applications
everywhere especially in finance in
economics stock markets and so on so if
you're are good at math if you
statistics is the well if you are
reasonably good at math statistics is
super super simple statistics is easy
and data science is all about statistics
of course I'm not saying data science is
just a ciwalk and all you will need
calculus you will need linear algebra
you will also need lots of statistics
and all matrices and all that so if you
are reasonably good at math then you can
certainly do well in data science and
data science is
lucrative you will find great
quantitative trading and all you create
algorithms that that model the stock
market and the behavior of various
stocks and indexes and all that so I
would say data science is great if you
want to make lots and lots of money look
at one great example the man who passed
away recently Jim Simons he is a b
multi-billionaire he has funded so many
scientific experiments the Simon
Observatory I had Dr Brian King on the
podcast a few weeks ago he was talking
about the Simon OB observatory in Chile
I believe and he has funded many other
scientific
experiments and he is a mathematician he
got a PhD at the age of what 22 23
something like that and he was in
Academia for a decade he is he made
significant very influential
contributions in
mathematics the churn Simons theory for
example but then he got bored of it he
quit he he started a quantitative
trading firm and he cracked the stock
market and incredible Returns His his
company got over the past I don't know
how many decades and he became a
multi-billionaire Simons Jim Simons so
he had the best of both worlds and
eventually he did return to mathematics
I mean one you have that sort of money
you can do anything the hell whatever
the hell you want so I would say the the
Practical approach to life is to ensure
you make a lot of money first and then
do whatever you want in life follow your
passions so I would say if you are a
practical person data science career
makes more sense than a career in pure
mathematics unless you're a Gregor
Perman or Shas ra ramanan type in that
case go for pure
mathematics okay h
okay
mlin geopolitics question what are my
views on Nancy Pelosi's visit to Tibet
is democracy coming to Tibet um my
friend Nancy Pelosi is not welcome in
Tibet she's not even welcome in China
which year was it was it last year or
the year before last uh
she paid a visit to Taiwan and the
Chinese protested very very vocally very
strongly and I assure you Nancy Pelosi
is not welcome in China and she's
definitely not welcome in Chinese
occupied Tibet Nancy Pelosi is on a
visit to India to bhat and from bhat she
has been making anti anti-china
statements so democracy is not coming to
Tibet anytime soon but Nancy Pelosi and
the Americans are trying to make sure
that the relationship between India and
China gets goes from bad to
worse because they want to push India
into a corner the Americans where India
has no option but to be on the American
side so on the one hand they will
extradite Indian Nationals to the US
after accusing them of of being
terrorists or or trying to assassinate
terrorists H they will accuse Indian
national an Indian national of trying to
assassinate a terrorist on American soil
a terrorist who is under American
protection then they will have that
person extradited to the US then they
will try to fuel a Civil War in Burma
and Manipur and Bangladesh
and then they will try to drive of
deeper wedge than what already exists
between India and China the Americans
are ensuring that India gets painted
into a
corner so that's what nany bosi her the
purpose of her of a visit to India is to
come to India give public speeches and
make statements that are inflammatory
from from the Chinese perspective I'm
not saying we are friends of China I'm
not saying that Chinese occupation of
Tibet is Justified and the Chinese also
have been been very provocative against
India of late so I suppose India may
have no option when it comes to the uh
relationship with China I don't think
it's it's a
relationship I don't think salvaging the
relationship is India's responsibility I
think China has to make some moves first
so overall that's where we are so Nancy
Pelosi hasn't visited Tibet she is on a
visit to India I think she's still in
India or may she may have just left
perhaps I'm not sure but she is using
this visit to make anti-china statements
from
India that's what's
happening
okay okay strangely proton has been
asking this question for a very very
long time okay here we have it the
question is why can't India make a great
wall around Pakistan and Bangladesh in
borders just like the US did in the
Mexican border okay let's go to the map
ah yes we have to go to map yes so where
is map uh oh wait I have to put that on
the map right one second here we are map
so here is the map so strangely proton
recommends that we go ahead and create a
big wall around
Pakistan okay starting from um the sir
Creek in Gujarat all the way to ladak
and encircle Pakistan by Afghanistan and
by Iran also so we encircle Pakistan
completely in a walls then we make
another wall around Bangladesh right so
another wall around Bangladesh including
the Bangladesh Burmese border so first
of all my
friend you can't go to the Afghanistan
Pakistan border and create a wall
there okay that is not Indian Territory
Afghanistan you can't even go to the
Iran Pakistan border and make a wall
there that is Iranian
territory when it comes to the India
Pakistan border yes one could construct
a wall now do you know how many
kilometers the India Pakistan
boundary is let me just take a very
rough thing let's let's measure the
distance in a straight line so the
straight line distance is 1,500 km if
you take all the zigzags and all the
twists and turns into consideration it
may be 2,000 plus kilometers do you know
how much money it takes to build a wall
That's 2,000 plus
kilometers and do you think that the
pakistanis will just sit there and allow
this to happen they will not indulge in
terrorism they will not indulge in
sniping and sabotage activities and if
you build a wall do you don't you think
it can be broken down in various places
by by the pakistanis they'll fire
Rockets or grenades or
whatever they will do
it right when it comes to the US and
Mexico the the Trump Administration did
build some walls I don't know whether it
is the uh Texas region or wherever it
was but they did do
that the entire border isn't walled off
but but there are sections of wall now
when it comes to the power asymmetry
between the US and Mexico the US is way
way more powerful than Mexico and the
Mexicans will not dare to run any kind
of proxy war against the us or any
Insurgency against the US from their
territory they'll be flattened if they
do that so the US has nothing to fear
from Mexico apart from the cartels that
they that the Americans are running in
Mexico allegedly but when it comes to
Pakistan and India it's a whole
different story so it is not practical
is my is my point once again with
Bangladesh actually we want Bangladesh
on our side the India Bangladesh
relationship is good I know there's a
gigantic horrifying problem of the
Bangladeshi infiltrators Who coming into
are coming into India that is a problem
that needs to be addressed I don't think
of wall is a solution I think
uh I think taking a deeper look at what
the BSF is doing is one solution taking
a look at what the border states of
India with Bangladesh are doing is
another solution and then identify and
expelling Bangladeshi infiltrators is a
is a third
solution so that is what needs to be
done the the wall thing is I think a
very rather impractical suggestion and
uh there are better ways of doing
things all
right shuti says what about Tam Tamil
nadu's current scenario are you talking
about the climate scenario weather are
you talking about the the music scene in
Tamil Nadu you mean the the ktic music
scene I talk about
the Western jazz music are talk about
the political scenario I talk about the
education scenario I talk about the
cultural
scenario the geological it's it's not a
geologically active Place actually Tamil
Nadu there's no earthquakes there uh
fishing agriculture what exactly are you
talking about my dear lady you to be
specific a little specific right only
then I can
answer all right
okay drun Kush Goa says why do you think
the Kashmir language sounds so different
from its neighboring states like Punjab
Etc it is what we call a darik language
it's part of the darik language family
which is which is a subset of the Indo
Arian language
family so the daric languages are
the baltistani language the Kashmir
language the uh there are a bunch of
languages in this region that's sound
very similar to each other so these
languages this the all these the
nuristani languages
Etc uh Etc they all sound very
similar and Sanskrit is sorry P what am
I saying Kashmir is one of them and if
you pay attention you will find that
Kashmir sounds kind of similar to
Persian also Persian Persian Parsi
language
but it's just the way it is but these
languages are all descended from the old
language Sanskrit so if it's there are
various languages in India groups of
languages that sound similar to each
other and kind of different from
others so the Kashmir language is part
of the
darik sublanguage family which is a
daughter language family of the Indo
Arian language family and that's why
these languages sound
similar just the way they've evolved
over
time
um I think I just answered this question
just a while ago so
you can check it
out tanay Chandra says I have seen a lot
of people posting a video of Saladin and
King Baldwin in praising the Brotherhood
of the Muslims and Christians what are
your views on it can you
explain how did somebody take a video of
Baldwin and salahadin
Albi
how that was what 12th century 11th
century I can't remember exactly when
somewhere around that time the Crusades
King Baldwin who had leprosy that guy
how did somebody take a video of those
guys it's not possible I suppose they
must be putting out clips of the movie
kingdom of
God right I suppose that's the one who
are the actors in that one of the actors
was Orlando Bloom Legolas from Lord of
the Rings another actress was Eva Green
who was in James Bond so I think they're
putting out clips of that movie not the
actual encounter
so I'm not aware of this first of all
now what's the deal between Saladin and
King Baldwin even Richard K Leon was
involved in this Richard the lionart and
Saladin praised him a lot and Richard
lion the lionard also pray Saladin a lot
there is some kind of Brotherhood
between what they call people of the
book okay the abrahamic religions there
is a lot of affinity between their World
Views and their
ideologies whether it's Islam whether
it's Christianity whether it's Judaism
these three these three religions are
very similar they all spring from the
same well they all have the same origin
the same
roots
and the Crusades was this period of time
when the Europeans under when the Europe
various European Kings uh under the
direction of the
Vatican went on this holy religious
mission to Liberate the Holy Land which
is presently Israel uh Lebanon
Etc from the Eastern
Mediterranean Seaboard essentially from
the so-called sarasin which is the the
Muslims and they succeeded from some for
some time they had the kingdom of
Tripoli Kingdom or whatever it was
called Tripoli and Antioch and whatever
principalities they had for some time
and then you had Saladin
Salah who has an interesting life story
himself he was once ruling in Egypt for
a while and so on so he kind of evicted
them and
then then the Europeans had to fight
back and all that but eventually the
Europeans were expelled from there and I
suppose there was a bit of respect from
on both sides for the bravery and the
Good Conduct of Saladin as well as
certain Europeans the Templars the
hospitaliers king Baldwin Richard the
lionard the King of England and so on so
that's what I can tell you I haven't
seen the clip so I can't comment
specifically but yes there is a lot of
affinity between these religions there's
very they're not very very very
different actually the abrahamic
religions um they have very similar
approaches World Views and all that so
yeah that could have contributed to
whatever respect Etc existed between the
two Waring sides
uh what
else sujan says was Christianity a voke
movement in ancient
Rome uh well one could perhaps look at
it that way you have an existing
civilizational structure cult you have
an existing culture and you want to
undermine and destroy that and the
actual object is not to replace one
culture with another the actual
objective is is is regime
change and to establish your own
regime so you you it's it's very easy to
use religion for that you know because
religion inflames passions especially if
you have a religion that spreads widely
and uh it it creates uh fanatical
followers why not use them why not use
that as as a tool as a as a means as a
vehicle to to power and then to
consolidate your power so that's what
Marxism is Marxism is a sociopolitical
toolkit I'm talking about Marxism I'll
come to Christianity okay I'm not
diverging somewhere so Marxism today's
Marxism is a sociopolitical toolkit that
is a very simple straightforward one
point
agenda to come to power and then to
remain in
power at the expense of everybody else
everybody else is current for so it
allows a very small group of people to
acquire political power and then
consolidate in that political power and
remain in political power that's the
only objective of Marxism but they have
this whole Great
Frame you know intellectual framework
built around that and very intellectual
sounding
language uh the dictatorship of the
proletariat the proletariat the lumpen
proletariat the
Bazi dialectical materialism and whatnot
it's all
BS all the only objective is that that
the small number of people who actually
are at the heart of things they want to
come to power and once they in power
they want to consolidate
power and uh it's all about
the it's all about the revolution isn't
it Marxism Revolution and who generally
runs a revolution who participates in
revolutions revolutions are are are
violent messy Affairs and generally when
a revolution happens in in with violence
it's the most violent people of society
who are at the Forefront of that and
then who do you think will emerge as the
leaders of that group the worst of the
lot right that's who comes to power when
there's a Marxist Revolution you've seen
that all over and over again what
happened in Cambodia Paul po came to
power you know what he
did what happened in the USSR what
happened in China incredibly horribly
history horrible history now once you
understand that what Marxism really is
and what its purpose is now let's talk
about what happened in ancient grp
you had this movement that had come out
of nowhere apparently about some prophit
from the Middle
East
yes and
uh and uh it started gaining currency
and they started playing the victim card
they know we are being oppressed we are
victims of
Oppression we are victims of Oppression
we demand equal
treatment you know we demand human
rights we are being oppressed we are
victims we are victims of some
phobia okay and then this gains currency
and then the the ruling Elite they see
this and they realize that this is going
to take over so if you can't beat them
join them so that's what Constantine did
he officially made Christianity the the
the state religion and he became
Christian and then everything changed so
you can say it's kind of a voke movement
it was kind of a voke movement then you
had another voke movement in France
later on much much much later on when
Napoleon was a teenager or on the brink
of his 20s the French Revolution there
was another voke movement there was
another mobocracy rule a violent
revolution led by
mobs and behind those mobs you had small
a small group of people who Hope to come
to power it didn't quite work out for
them that way but France went full woke
after that so the French Revolution was
another woke Revolution essentially and
France disposed got rid of its
aristocracy the the people who actually
set the standards in France and today
you have a whole set of different
standards in France you have Lac and
whatnot so so yes you could say that
Christianity can be considered to be
kind of a voke movement in ancient Rome
a voke movement that did succeed and
totally destroyed the old ways
polytheism the old culture of Rome
everything was wiped out and what
happened to Rome
crumbled Rome crumbled it never regained
its former greatness the Byzantine
Empire the Eastern Roman Empire
continued for a while and let's say a
thousand years more
roughly but it never really did anything
great until it itself fell to the
Turks all right
okay HED Patel says what are your
thoughts on procuring s57 su75 from
Russia since amca is about 15 years away
what will be the trade sanctions on
Russia and Barat will the US support it
the US will never support anything that
benefits Russia or India for that
matter so see recently we uh acquired
the a terminal on the port of chabahar
for 10 years on a 10 year lease from
Iran 10 year Le 10 years is this much
right the Americans threatened India
with sanctions they've already
sanctioned Iran horribly now they're
threatening India with s with sanctions
so if India procures let's say a big
order the Su 57 or su75 or whatever
whatever from Russia they may the
Americans May sanction India now the
question is let's say the American
sanctions may not happen so should we
procure this aircraft I don't know I
think that that um if we if we are to
procure something we should there's a
huge problem if you have too many
different kinds of
aircraft okay because it makes your life
miserable you to procure spare paths
from 75 different
countries it's a nightmare it's a
logistical nightmare you have to train
Engineers on so many different aircrafts
so you need to have more engineers and
each specializes in one kind of aircraft
it's it's an absolute nightmare we
already have so many aircraft it's like
a miner it's like a zoo of aircraft the
mig21 we had the Mig 25 which is now
um phased out the MiG 29 Mig 31 do we
have it perhaps we have the suo 30 mki
you have the
Jaguar um what is we have the
Tas I'm sure I'm missing one or two here
and there fighter
planes so that's already a huge number
of aircraft different kinds of aircraft
and all foreign aircraft apart from from
the thees thees now you acquire one more
suo 3 57 or suo 75 one more new type of
aircraft you to learn how to handle and
to maintain and you procure spare spare
parts from Russia because some spare
parts they won't allow us to build
here I don't think it's worth worth the
hassle so if we need more aircraft get
more
Rafal we have we have what 36 roughly
I'm I suppose all 36 must have reached
India by now so we had an order of 36
let's say they've all reach here reach
India by now if we need more aircraft as
a stop Gap measure get a 100 Rafal I
know no it will cost money everything
cost money get those or FS if you place
a large order the French may even be
willing to shift the production line to
India to move the prod production line
to India or at least establish a
production line in India the French are
very amenable to reasonable discussions
or they can be slightly unreasonable at
times like everybody can but they are
more amenable to cooperation with India
compared to a nation like the US let's
say so I would say we should not go for
the Su 57 or su75 or or any new aircraft
go with something you already have and
already know how to handle so if we need
more aircraft go for the
Gaal I would say go for 100 of those or
even 200 if you have the money get a
whole bunch of those those are really
good
planes okay
vishaka vishaka kabila says I'm
sorry vishaka Kaba says how safe is
Egypt to travel to
in terms of the current scenario of the
world for
Indians
uh good
question you know I think in Egypt is a
wonderful country great ancient culture
and great food great
everything in today's world I would be
personally reluctant to go to
Egypt because we've had terrorist
attacks over there in North Africa
various places you've heard of cruise
ships getting targeted you've heard of
foreign tourists being targeted even if
it happens once or twice it's enough to
to put multiple question marks in your
head so if you were to ask me will I go
to would I be happy to go to Egypt today
next week next month this year I would
say maybe not maybe not so that's what I
can tell you from my pers perspective I
would rather not go to Egypt right
now uh there are some countries I would
certainly want to certainly be happy to
go to but right now Egypt probably not
okay techn says why can't India make
skyscrapers like the borju Khalifa and
other skyscrapers all great skyscrapers
all around the world I think India also
has skyscrapers how tall is the BJ
Khalifa shall we uh try and see let's go
to our friend
Google uh let me
um put the on the screen BJ Khalifa So
BJ Khalifa is a skyscraper in Dubai the
UAE it's the world's tallest structure
828 M
tall 163 floors okay so that's a
reasonably tall building what's the
tallest building in India I
wonder uh
tallest India
is the tallest building
apparently and this one is 828 okay so
it's a it's
significantly uh taller than India's
tallest
building the the question
is what do you get by building
enormously tall buildings it needs to
have
a financial economic Etc
justification and India right now is a
lwi income
Nation a global South Country third
world country do we need buildings of
that class right now if we build that
sort of a building what do we get out of
it is the question I'm sure we can build
we can construct such buildings but what
is the financial economic payback that
we get so the bush Khalifa is in a first
world nation
the UAE has one of the highest living
standards in the
world very you go to you go to the US U
it's like if India was run properly and
if India was at the first world nation
that's how it would look like that's the
feeling you
get so in a nation like the UA it may
make sense to have a b Khalifa kind of
building a sevenstar hotel I believe it
is and I'm sure it is uh financially
uh profitable I suppose so India
certainly can build it but do we need to
build it is the question so it's not
like we are missing out on something by
not building 800 900 ft meter tall
buildings we're not missing out on
anything we have many tall buildings in
India I think Mumbai Delhi Etc Bangalore
I suppose we could have big buildings
but uh maybe in the future it may happen
we already have this fetish for the
world's largest statues don't we so we
should be happy with that we have a
statue of what's the guy what's what's
his name Mr Patel
the world's largest statue right
yay and yeah it's great for tourism Etc
I haven't been there personally but yeah
so we have the tallest statues in the
world I'm sure we building more tall
statues not sure what we get out of it
but
okay
um T Chandra says do you think Israel
and the Western Powers will take back
Bethlehem and merge with Israel
Bethlehem is in the West Bank isn't it
let's go to the map Bethlehem is the
West Bank it's
uh what do you get by taking it back
look Bethlehem is the I think the
birthplace of Mr Jesus
right and
uh okay let's just Google
it Bethlehem is it West Bank is it where
is it
okay it's an Israel
proper okay
so is it Bethlehem of Galilee or is it
just
Bethlehem yeah as I thought it's in the
West
Bank so the the question is what does
Israel
gain by taking back Bethlehem what do
Western Powers gain by taking be back
Bethlehem I don't see any geopolitical
benefit I don't see any uh economic
Financial
benefit and from Israel's perspective I
don't see them perceiving any cultural
benefit or civilizational benefit either
from taking back Bethlehem because
Israel is a Jewish Nation it's not a
Christian
Nation and Mr Jesus who was born in
Bethlehem was well he's the founder of
Christianity isn't he the prophet of
Christianity not sure the Israelis are
this they see has one of their own and
the Western powers are
now what do we mean by the Western
Powers there are no Western Powers
there's only one Western power the US
the US is kind of distancing itself now
from Christianity isn't
it so I don't see any uh I don't see
them wanting to take this back or seeing
any benefit in taking it
back panage prajapati says if in if both
India and China historically shared the
same values and thought processes why is
it that the people of China are willing
to accept a monarchy while Indians are
so obsessed with democracy the simple
answer is the education system is
brainwashed
Indians you can take the most civilized
people of the in the world and in just a
few Generations turn them into absolute
what is a polite word what's a polite
word okay let's turn them into absolute
simplon I think simpleton is a simp is a
is a polite enough word I had other
words in mind but I won't use
those so it you can be the most
civilized people in the world if you
have an education system like what we
have in India you can use that and in
just four five six Generations turn the
entire nation into a nation of
simpletons brainwashed
simpletons so that's where we are today
today's Indians have no connection with
the world of their ancestors they have
no connection with their own culture
they believe everything their teachers
and textbooks teach them ah democracy
secularism democracy secularism and when
I say democracy I'm not I'm not
disparaging democracy India is the
origin of democ democracy but we had a
different form of democracy this
revolving door democracy every 5 years
complete uncertainty in what happens to
the nation that is a disaster for
India
okay and dictatorship could be an even
bigger disaster first of all we have to
understand that if you have a na if you
have a ruler like K Mama who's a
dictator imagine what happens to you if
you have maong as a dictator imagine
what happens so I'm not saying
dictatorship is the Panacea to to the
ills of democracy we need to have better
system so Indians are obsessed with
secularism with democracy with with
whatever the Western values are Indians
are obsessed with that because of the
education system Indians are good people
and those
who who are in favor of whatever the
West is teaching them they actually feel
that they are right and they are they
they mean well for the country so the
ones who have this leftist liberal
mindset and all they are not bad people
they are well-meaning people they're all
Indians and they're all well-meaning
people and they think they're on the
right path because they're great
teachers and their great textbooks
taught them this stuff and the great
Media news news readers tell them all
this and the great politicians they
Admire have have been espousing these
causes so you see the when you have a
disastrous ridiculously bad garbage like
education system you can turn an entire
nation into a nation of simplon that's
the situation in India today and it's
getting worse by the day
okay in the case of china they have been
steadfastly improving their education
system since the
1980s they have invested trillions of
dollars worth of money since the 1980s
into their education system and they
make it a point to inculcate a strong
sense of of
patriotism in in the
children and and and pride in their
culture and the Communist party also of
course so that's the difference it's the
simple difference is the education
system the education system I've been
saying for years we need to reform it
nothing is being
done
so
okay aush says I am from Bihar biharis
are not treated well and look down upon
as if they are only for labor class work
people make fun of the bihari accent and
using instead of May I wonder where is
UN unity and diversity I don't think
everybody makes fun of people from biar
you it depends on the people you're
around the people who you surround
yourself with or you are you find
yourself surrounded with I do not
believe that everybody makes fun of
biharis the way I see Bihar is I from my
perspective Bihar is magad magad is the
seat of many empires that have ruled
India mag has given India many wonderful
extremely great
Emperors magad gave India vishnugupta
chanakya magad gave India Chandra gupt
Maia Ashok the great the great Gupta
Emperors samudra Gupta the great
conqueror and so many more skandagupta
who defended India against wave after
wave of honik invasions so many more why
did Bihar go down the path it went it
has gone down because the British
destroyed Bihar first the Turks
destroyed Bihar then the British
destroyed it even f and after 1947 the
politicians did not do anything to to
revive Bihar and that's why Bihar is
that is where it is today Bihar is so
many different local dialects and
languages is isn't that something that
tells you how rich the old culture
is
so once again it boils down to the
education system once again it boils
down to India's rotten education system
we don't teach our kids the rich history
of various parts of India so that's why
you are all you only have St type stuck
in your
head if if kids are taught the history
of various parts of India including the
incredibly Rich history of Bihar the
great glorious history of biar you think
this attitude will be there no it won't
be there but the education system is
rotten it's garbage and our wonderful
leaders are doing nothing to reform it
so don't blame I know if you are bihari
and you you face these situations you
will obviously feel very
upset but since I'm not be I'm not
emotionally invested in this so from the
way I see it from above is that it's not
the fault of these people they simply
don't know they are
ignorant and they have only seen the
negative
stereotypes so that's why this situation
persists what needs to happen is we need
to reform the education system and teach
our future generations and the current
Generations India's real history and
then they will realize how incredibly
great Bihar is even the people of Bihar
probably won't know what their own
history
is do the people of Patna know that they
are living in patliputra the historic
patliputra I suppose some of them would
know but they don't know what it means
actually what was partly Putra
like so yeah and I would say that the
people of Bihar they should be commended
that instead of doing nothing they at
least do labor work if they have no
other
choice they have the enterprising Spirit
to move far away from their Homeland and
go to far off States in search of work
and they do an honest days labor and and
and earn money honestly and also send
much of the money back to their
family isn't that something that is
worthy of a great amount of
respect so we have to look at the world
differently I would urge people who may
have this attitude please please reframe
your worldview if if if somebody is
doing labor
work well that person is doing honest
work isn't he he's not stealing he's not
leeching of the government that I am
this I'm this class or that Minority and
I want this much money no these people
are doing honest work they are worthy of
respect that's how I see it
sir okay okay let's see what else
rajet choa says how can Barat deal with
the illegal immigrant crisis ascending
the sending them back would be a gig
gigantic logistical challenge the whole
ecosystem attacked barhat during CA can
this be prevented in the future look we
have two choices either we absorb them
all and become completely different or
we deal with this
problem I remember around 2014 they were
saying there are 50 million 5 CR
Bangladesh's in India illegal
Bangladesh's
today the number would have doubled I
would say let's say it's a 100 million a
100 million is larger than the
population of most
countries I know that sending them all
back would be a logistical
challenge I don't care it's not my
problem it is the government's problem I
cannot go and evict Bangladesh is right
I don't have the authority or the
power so the so the people of
India are not in a position to address
this problem the only entity that that
is in a position and that is authorized
and empowered to address the problem is
the government of
India and Promises have been made that
Bangladesh will be sent back what
happened to those
promises they have to be sent back to
Bangladesh they will if they are allowed
to stay in India they will become Indian
citizens they will acquire documents
they will
multiply way faster than Indians and in
a new generations India will become a
new
Bangladesh I have nothing against
Bangladesh I wish the people of
Bangladesh the
best I wish to have great relations with
Bangladesh
extremely favorable mutually favorable
relations I want Bangladesh to prosper
but I want the Bangladesh's who have
come to India illegally to go back to
their country where they can prosper
when Bangladesh prospers and we will
help Bangladesh Prosper but the ones who
have come into India illegally need to
be went back now if the government did
nothing the past so many
years then it is their fault that there
are so many in in India and they have to
find a solution they can't just sit back
and say we can't do anything anymore
then we'll vote them out of power right
obviously if they can't do it somebody
else can do
it
so how can this be addressed is the
question
right um I'm sure there are ways and
means I think every Indian knows where
when you run into a Bangladeshi you just
know
it so it's not hard to identify them
let's say they have papers documents you
can do a little bit of investigation and
discover where those documents were
acquired from when the government wants
to do something they can trace
everything out I promise you
that okay when they go after somebody
they can trace out their entire life
history and the life history of their
past 11
Generations so they are capable of doing
it so let's use that for some national
good for a change right so you need to
identify these people and then find ways
and means of sending them back
peacefully we don't
want we don't want any harm to to happen
to them we just want them to go back so
give yourself let's say one year to
identify all the illegals and give
yourself two years two years more to
send them all back in an orderly
systematic manner that's it and we have
good relations with the Bangladesh
government we can discuss it out and U
come to a mutually acceptable logical
logistical
solution okay so many questions so many
questions ronit sahu says how to master
a subject let's say
Finance just by reading
books the way to master any subject is
first first by acquiring theoretical
knowledge quickly as quickly as you can
and then start you have to start solving
problems start getting
practical okay which means you to get
your hands dirty you to get into it so
let's say you let's let's take some
examples let's say you want
to
um you want to learn how to play cricket
you're going to read a book you're going
to go in practice obiously going to go
in practice bowling batting Fielding
whatever let's say you want to learn how
to build how to construct buildings yeah
you can learn about the physics the the
mechanics of it the load bearing and all
that the Cy lbers and all that stuff how
much weight goes where and what is the
area and dimensions and all that stuff
but then you once you acquire that basic
theoretical knowledge you go and start
building you start making scale models
and then bigger models and all that and
sometimes you'll fail sometimes you
succeed and you will learn from the
failures so the way to master any
subject is to do it practically
if you want to be a good speaker public
speaker you think you can read 50 books
about that and become overnight a good
speaker no you do it over and over again
you practice practice practice initially
you practice all alone in front of a
mirror perhaps then you practice in
front of your three friends or your
siblings then you gather the courage and
go in front of an audience of 10 people
and you do that 50 times then you start
doing it in front of larger audiences
you to do it over and over and over
again if you want to be a good public
speaker you need to give at least a 100
bad
speeches okay it's a difficult
process so that's how you do it you
master a subject by through practice
through practical
practice not by reading books reading
books will give you a very vague
theoretical uh understanding you want to
attain Nirvana you think you will attain
Nirvana by by reading books about
Nirvana how how you feel when you reach
there and how Buddha what process the
Buddha use to reach nirvana no you reach
nirvana or you try to reach nirvana by
doing anapan Vash or whatever form of
meditation so that's what you do you can
only Master something by doing that
thing so if you want to master Finance
you do Finance whatever it is trading so
let's say you want to be in the stock
market you want to become a great day
trader or whatever it is quantitative
Trader whatever it is
okay you read books you watch YouTube
videos and whatever you read lots of
books you get a proper understanding
then what do you do do you stake your
entire 10 lakh Rupees of wealth on the
stock market
no you start with 10,000 rupees a month
small small small allocations of stocks
and then you see how it goes you you
start very small and you see how you're
doing and whether your experiments are
working or not and over time you develop
the understanding and patterns start
forming in your mind that's how you do
it so you master subjects through action
not through
Theory
um rasi rajaj
says why are Indian youngsters so
unconfident is it due to bad parenting
or education system I don't blame the
parents the education system is so back
breakingly horrible that a kid has to
study spend five six hours a day in
school or college and then spend another
seven eight hours doing homework and
then going to tution classes or whatever
they hardly get to see their parents
it's not the parents fault okay some
parents will be good some may be not so
good but overall it's not the fault of
the parents first of all there is that
so when you have such an enormous
pressure on you all you are expected to
do all you are forced to do is study
study study then you will never go
out in the open and L anything physical
any physical activity so physic Ally you
will not be strong fit athletic whatever
right your diet Also may not be good
because in the Indian diet is the
starvation diet over the which we have
acquired over the past 200 years the
original Indian diet from before the
European era was very different Indians
ate a very different diet today it's all
carbohydrates carbohydrates
carbohydrates which we think is our
tradition one of the traditions in India
is the sabudana ky sabana ky during
fasting first of all when you fast
you're not supposed to eat food secondly
sabudana kiter is not even Indian it is
tapioka tapa flower which comes from
sago Sago is a Southeast Asian thing
okay and uh these days you make it from
from tapioka which is a root that is a
substitute for Sago so all this entire
tradition of sabudana kri began in the
20th century there is not the sabudana
balls are not Indian it's not an Indian
food you know in Southeast Asia they
have bubble tea or whatever that has the
same thing T tapa balls so this has come
in from Southeast Asia but we think it's
an Indian tradition to eat tabudi so the
diet is terrible it's it's extremely
carbohydrate heavy very little protein
so Indian
boys there there's no muscle mass you
don't get the time to go to gym you
don't go to play football lift weights
do wrestling kaby Cricket whatever throw
javelins a boxing match or whatever
nothing no physical activity whatever
so because of these factors and
because so the combination of all these
factors and then you have the education
system that that infuses inculcates a
sense of inferiority overall in all
Indians so because of all these things
Indian youngsters are not as confident
as they should be like what's a
confident young man or woman going to be
like somebody who can go out and do
something physical and also has good
grades and studies and all that that you
don't have that right you're you have an
entirely onedimensional childhood study
study study study study what do you get
out of it at the end of it all a 9 to5
job or 9 to9 job with little salary
that's all you get out of it so these
are the reasons why many Indian
youngsters are not confident enough
first of all physically they're just not
strong they're just not healthy the diet
is terrible they don't do any physical
activity and all that so once again the
root cause is the education system this
horrible education system how many times
do you have to tell the government
please do something about it please
please please reform
it
now Karan nwat says what's your views on
the Lego India project it's called
Indigo I think it will start by let's
say 2075 or something maybe 2085
definitely in the 21st century it'll
start
that's my view about it I am confident
we will make it happen in the 21st
century before the year 2100 it will
become
operational
okay Salon Dynasty says if the vdas
contain a lot of knowledge as we have
heard from a lot of historians and
Saints why didn't they mention the
existence of dinosaurs look the V what
are the vas the vas are the oldest
literature that we know of in the world
okay the world's oldest known literature
dates back several thousand years and
what the vas talk about what the vas
offer us is first of all a snapshot of
the Society of our
ancestors a societ a snapshot of the
ancient Indian society as it existed
several thousand years ago it was um a
pastor Al Society nonurban Society rural
society and you had various Clans the
population was much lower than smaller
than what it is today in the
subcontinent and so on and it talks
about the the philosophy and
spirituality and religion of the of the
time the various gods that we worshiped
the Vic Pantheon of gods it it talks
about the origin of the universe the
nasad sukta speak about this and so on
so it all offers a fascinating glimpse
into a very ancient Society our society
the Society of our ancestors that's
where we come from that's our heritage
the vas are not books of
science okay the vdas are not scientific
texts please understand
that they don't talk about quantum
mechanics
relativity uh mechanics
Dynamics whatever they don't talk about
these things they don't offer you
Solutions onto how to solve physics or
architectural or whatever chemical
problems or whatever that's not what the
vas are about the vas are a Priceless
treasure but they are not scientific
books
and and please understand that they do
speak about
dinosaurs the vas speak about
dinosaurs they speak about the dinosaurs
which we still see today
there are dinosaurs outside my my
building so they do speak about those
Dinosaurs the Aven
Dinosaurs the Aven dinosaurs they don't
speak about the non-avian dinosaurs
because the non-avian dinosaurs died out
66 million years ago when no humans
existed so the vas only speak about what
existed a few thousand years ago and the
non-avian dinosaurs did exist you know
what the non Avan dinosaurs are called
today they're called
Birds suit statement says how did the
Arians get settled here in Nepal are we
immigrants or Invaders or are we Native
what's our history
look what are the
Arians AR
Ian we this is what happens when you
have a completely rotten education
system we think of this term Arya the
Sanskrit term Arya as as an
ethnic uh
term Arya is not an
ethnicity the Europeans see Arya as
ethnicity they have stolen that term
from us from us the the people of the
subcontinent
the from the European perspective the
Arian word means the white people they
have stolen that word at the term from
us the only people who can be called the
ARA people are the people of the
subcontinent and the people of
Persia these are the only true ARA
people in the entire universe the
Europeans the Nordic people the Germanic
tonic Celtic whatever people are anaria
they are not Arya at all the term Arya
is a Sanskrit word it means Noble it
means
Superior and today we call each other
sir right we call somebody sir in the
old days our ancestors called each other
Arya so it meant sir it meant somebody
who is worthy of respect it did not
exactly mean sir it meant ARA you can't
actually translate that it meant
somebody who's Noble and Superior and
refined and cultured and civil ized
that's what it meant so the true Aras
are the people of the subcontinent and
their Persian
descendants so the people of Nepal are
the original ARA just like the other
people of
India and the true natives of India are
the Arya which is
us we are not the product of some Arian
Invasion or migration or tourism or
picnic we are the natives of the
subcontinent we have been around for at
least 70,000 years that's our history
that's what genetics tells
you the
oldest matenal as well as patrilineal
lineages genetic lineages Hao groups in
the world originated in the Indian
subcontinent Hao group f for the males
65 or so thousand years ago originated
in the Indian subcontinent and Hao
groups M and MN which are female
matrilineal H Hy groups also originated
in the Indian
subcontinent so the people of India are
not the product of some migration or
invasion of wh- skinned Arian we are the
original Arya the original Arya are
these people the brown skinned people
the darkhaired Dark Eyed
people we are the original inhabitants
and the same goes for Nepal obviously
you also part of the subcontinent
Indians and nepales are the same people
more or less no real difference and the
Persians were our cousins now the
genetics of Persia have kind of changed
after the the turkey after the Arabic
and turky occupation of Iran that's a
different story okay so the ARA settled
in Nepal and batsh overall about 70
80,000 years before
today we are the original
natives
okay um
let us
see okay rice
says why do some Israelis hate Netanyahu
isn't he working to end
Hamas why do some Americans hate Trump
why do some French people hate maon why
do some Italian people hate Madame
milone why do some Indians hate Mr
Modi you will
as you grow up in life you will find
that you can never make everyone love
you you can't please
everybody you just do what you believe
is the right thing to
do okay and if the majority of the
nation is with you then you will get
elected to the highest Post in the
nation but there'll always be a
significant amount of people who will
not like you who will hate
you so nathania who well is a
complicated figure very interesting Guy
Mr bamin Netanyahu his brother Yuni
Netanyahu was a Commando in the Israeli
Special Forces he was killed in
operation
anbe in
U
Tanzania now nany is a long political
career Etc he is said to be a corrupt
politician alleged to be a corrupt poit
politician my question to you my dear
friends is that apart from a very small
minority
globally apart from a very small
minority in most Nations do you do you
see too many politicians who don't have
allegations of corruption against
them in India there's there's just a
handful of politicians who have the
reputation that they don't have a single
allegation of corruption and I really
appreciate that but most politicians
over time some of the other allegations
will be thrown at you and some of them
may be right perhaps in some cases in
some in the case of some politicians so
there are allegations of corruption
against Mr Netanyahu and he try he has
been trying to reform the Israeli
judicial
system and take away some of the powers
because the Judiciary is
unelected the Israeli Judiciary has
tremendous Powers despite being an
unelected body they can actually come
and uh interfere in the ACT acts of the
government in the parliament which is
actually a danger to democracy whether
you realize it or not when you have an
unelected institution that gains power
over the elected institution that is
dangerous for democracy so he's actually
trying to rectify that but yeah there is
a hatred there is hatred towards him for
that he seen as too far right wi because
there is a significant left wing in
Israel now among the Jews also and so on
so there it's a complicated thing lots
of factors but my simple answer is that
there will be no politician in the world
who is universally loved or universally
hated even the most popular politicians
in the country in any country we have a
significant percentage of the population
that doesn't like them so that's just uh
the nature of the world and the nature
of
politics
okay banku Nat Singh says what's your
favorite cricket match of all time one
from your era and one from the current
ERA what is my ERA this is my era isn't
it I don't know I've seen so many
cricket matches I've I've been
watching Cricket since I think the first
World Cup I've watched was
92 I was a kid then but I watched the 92
World Cup and India beat Pakistan in
that that was a good one one of the only
matches India won in the entire world
cup AAR Udin was the captain then
so so there was that the 96 World Cup we
defeated Pakistan there was a good good
match really good match the venketesh
Prasad Amir soel
thing and and uh yeah many I think the
2007 World Cup T20 World Cup great
matches in there we beat Pakistan twice
in one match against Pakistan we won
30-0 imagine a three- score in a cricket
match but we defeated Pakistan 3-0 in in
a group match in the final match what
a what hard stopping match it was and
that iconic missar shot in India in the
semi-final India beat Australia Yad
Singh play played really well so there's
been so many great cricket
matches um some matches don't even
involve India the the 434 match South
Africa Australia that was a great one so
yeah and I've seen really great players
some of the greatest players of all time
West Indies used to be a great force in
the past ctly Ambrose one of the great
Bowlers so I've seen lots of matches but
yeah these days I don't follow Cricket
that much because it's become kind of
boring now it doesn't have I watch
international cricket but not the IPL
not much it's a
yeah okay sh ramachandra says tell us
about autoimmune diseases how do they
occur are they cured through current
genetic technology how do you prevent
your generation from acquiring them see
autoimmune dis what is an autoimmune
disease it is a disease in which your
immune system becomes hyperactive and
overreacts about something and the
overreaction is such that it attacks its
own
body so it's kind of similar to an
allergy but allergy is towards harmless
foreign substances so some people have
allergy of
what pollen peanut allergies some people
if they eat peanuts or if they eat
shellfish like shrimps or prawns or
something they get allergies that SW
face swells up tongue swells up and all
that they have to be given some what
antihistamines and all that so that's an
allergy in which a harmless external
substance is perceived as a as a is a
mortal Threat by the immune system it
overreacts and then it causes all these
uh symptoms inflammation and all that
various kinds of inflammation that's an
allergy asthma is an allergy allergic
rinitis is an allergy and so on so forth
so on so forth pollen allergies and all
that but autoimmune diseases are
diseases in which the immune system
behaves very similarly it overreacts but
instead of attacking a harmless foreign
substance it attacks your own tissues
so that's an autoimmune disease what I
forget the what are some common
autoimmune diseases arthritis arthritis
is an autoimmune
disease people you know that the joints
the cartilage in the joints gets
destroyed over time I think it's an
autoimmune disease if I'm not mistaken
and there are some other autoimmune
diseases whose names I can't remember
right now what is it I forget I forget
but yeah so that's what an autoimmun
disis is your immune system
attack attacks your own tissues for
whatever reason uh I'm not sure what the
Cure is for autoimmune diseases can you
do some I think there could be a genetic
reason for that maybe it's some acquired
inherited genetic thing
perhaps um so it it's possible that it
could be cured through
genetic what genetic engineering or
whatever uh but I'm not sure if any
known cures exist for the most prominent
autoimmune diseases I'm sure it's an
area of active
research but that's what I can tell
you aloh homur says why doesn't India or
the Indian government focus on Atomic
power plants or energy we haven't been
able to achieve atomic energy targets
ever regardless of whichever government
is in power uh yeah I agree see nuclear
energy is green energy as long as you
have a
good reactor and you have good processes
and all that as long as you have good
technology it's going to be completely
perfectly safe so nuclear energy
is abundant it's an abundant source of
energy as long as you have the nuclear
Fuel and it's completely green the
nuclear waste can be disposed of very
safely and uh apart from solar it's it's
one of the cleanest forms of energy and
solar and wind energy geothermal energy
Etc these are unreliable sources of
energy because they depend on external
factors nuclear energy is completely
reliable so India should focus on
nuclear energy we have a three-stage
nuclear program we are just getting into
the second stage the third stage is
Thorium based
reactors we have an abundance of Thorium
in India we have the world's largest
reserves of thorium we should have 500
nuclear
reactors overall eventually right now
how many do we have a handful
so uh when when you look at upcoming
nuclear reactors and reactors under
construction I think India is one of the
top Nations right now the Chinese are at
the Forefront they may have about 50
reactors being planned and 2030 being
built right now I think India comes
second or third if if I'm not mistaken
in the world but India needs
to India India can do so much more so I
agree with you that India should focus
on nuclear power India has the world's
largest thorium deserves it is a gift
that the gods have given us why not
leverage that why not use that so I
don't know why the the three- stage
program is lagging so far behind
probably politicians are busy with more
important pressing agendas and and
long-term energy security may not be
that important for for them perhaps
because it doesn't give them
votes well in a democracy every 5 years
you need to go and ask for votes and if
you said that I am constructing 25
nuclear power power plants people won't
understand because the educ tion system
is garbage and the people won't
understand what it means so once again
you have to reform the education system
I think every answer that I give it
comes back to the education system
that's how dire a need we have in India
of reforming the education system so
maybe one of the reasons politicians
aren't incentivized to double down on
the nuclear program is because most
Indians won't understand what it is and
and and and other political parties will
claim that they you trying to damage the
environment recently I mean not recently
about decade or so years decade or so
ago there
was a scientif a physics Observatory a
physics experiment that was going to be
built in India a neutrino
Observatory okay a neutrino Observatory
and some political parties raised the
human cry saying that it will it will
pollute water with nuclear fuel or
something like that it'll it will
pollute the environment with nuclear
fuel absolute nonsense but it it alarmed
the public of that place and I think the
the experiment never took off so that is
how um ill educated the Indian public is
so then if you try to if you spend a lot
of money building nuclear power plants
it won't translate to votes so I think
that's the reason why politicians don't
have the incentive to double down on the
Indian nuclear program because it's not
something that gains them votes on the
other hand if you go give freebies and
if you go give free laptops and you give
free this connection that connection it
may get you
vs see that's the quality of the Indian
public that's the quality of the Indian
education system we need to change that
but nobody's bothered to do
it mclin says uh should I take whey
protein how is Amal way look wayy
protein is protein that comes from a
dairy Source when you see when you have
milk let's say you have a liter of milk
and you want to make paneer so that's a
process right and then you can squeeze a
lime or lemon into the into the milk so
it'll split curdle the milk and then you
take a fine cloth and
you and you put the milk in that and or
or you keep it overnight and by the
morning all the liquid comes out and all
the solid is out and that is paneer
cottage cheese and the liquid that comes
down that's called whey and there's a
lot of protein in there and that's
processed to extract the protein and
that's way protein so it's a good source
of protein as long as the company is
good and they've not put any garbage in
there so if you buy V protein from a
reputed company it's going to be good
for you it's going to be very high
quality protein one scoop will have 20
25 grams of protein you take two scoops
a day you get 50 grams like just like
that just two scoops reasonable size so
if you are lifting if you want to gain
muscle mass and you if you if your diet
doesn't give you sufficient protein if
you're vegetarian or whatever you can
take way protein it's a vegetarian
source of protein it's good amul amul is
a good company as far as I understand so
amul could be good I suppose so yes I
think it is something that can certainly
help you pack on some muscle mass and
and reach your protein Targets in case
you have a protein deficient diet or
because of various reasons you don't get
enough protein so yes you can go for a
good protein Source I think uh amul way
protein should be good amul is a reputed
company for
sure okay
Shri balam Putin G says just out of
curiosity why did most of the Gods
choose India as their birthplace and
hence we are the only surviving
civilization till date which we are not
but s your
thoughts
well who knows what goes on in the minds
of the Gods the gods live so far
above we are down here we are mere
Mortals how how are we to
know what that thought process is so why
did
Indra choose India as his birthplace I
don't know if I meet Indra I'll ask him
if I'm lucky enough to meet him if I am
worthy enough and blessed enough to to
have an audience with Shri Indra Lord
Indra then I will certainly ask him but
there must be something great about
India's land this this
sacred holy land that induced all the
gods to to take their birth in bhatar
that's what I would imagine uh but why
what was the thought process behind that
why did they choose to be born here only
they can tell if I am lucky enough if
I'm fortunate enough to meet them I
shall certainly ask them and I shall get
back to you and do a get back here and
do a special ask Abit session okay but
my thoughts is that are that most likely
this is a very holy sacred place for
some reason and that's why the Gods to
be born here the good Gods at least the
good
Gods
okay
uh everything Beyond says as a normal
citizen of India how can I change the
Indian education system and reduce crime
rate in
India you do that by becoming a great
person rising to India's top position
and then pushing through the
reforms you can only see if you want to
make a change in the world of any
kind um the more powerful and the we the
wealthier you are the more powerful you
are the greater a change you can bring
about so if you are a
person who has no political power you
can make you can make almost no change
in the world if you're a person of very
limited wealth then your impact will be
very limited so the lesser the power and
the lesser the wealth that is at your
disposal the Lesser is going to be your
impact on the world if you want to
change the entire education system of a
subcontinent sized Nation you have to
acquire immense political power and
immense wealth you don't need to have to
acquire that wealth yourself as an
individual you can become a part of a
political party that has access to that
much wealth and power and then you rise
in that political party and you rise to
the top position then you can do make a
change so that's the only way you can
change the education system reduce crime
rates get out of get rid of infiltrators
whatever change the borders of India any
big change if you want to do you have to
rise to an incredibly powerful position
only then you can do it otherwise you
can keep on
striving but unfortunately the the
impact that you will have is going to be
very
limited all
right okay
techn says why hasn't the Indian
government why can't the government
allocate enough money or a sufficient
budget for the space research program I
think if they allocate minimum $5
billion budget to Israel then we can
work much faster and Achieve new
Milestones there is another one of my
constant refrains India needs to be a
leader in the Space
Race India cannot afford to get left
behind but once again it's not not
on a high priority when it comes to
politics
because if you let's say you allocated
lots of money okay let's say you are the
Indian Prime Minister and you allocate
$5 billion to the to the Space Program
to is and ISRO launches uh does multiple
human space launches with that okay it
sends
five five missions into space manned
missions okay and we also build a let's
say a space station in orbit around the
Earth so we do a lot of stuff with this
$5 billion so at the end of five years
the Prime Minister goes to the public
and says see I did this I have spent so
much money on ISRO and we have achieved
this is this and then his opponents
political opponents will say you didn't
do anything the scientists did it why
are you taking
credit right and then what will the
Prime Minister say and the people will
believe it they'll believe various
YouTubers say
it is a scientists who are doing
everything he's just taking credit for
it so then the question is when you have
limited resources as a politician why
will you spend it on something that will
not give you bring you votes
unfortunately in the democratic system
of India it is imperative for a
politician to get
votes that's why I keep saying this is
not the right system for India I'm not
saying we should have a dictatorship I I
mean we should have a better system so
that's the reason why the space program
is on the back burner we're going to
have some small progress here and there
by 2035 2040 we may have a space station
by 2025 26 we may have the first human
space flight perhaps and by 2040s we may
have touch down on the moon humans
perhaps if things go to plan it's all
far in the future we we never know right
now if I was the Prime Minister I would
certainly do it but I may not get get
elected again after five years
so that that that's how it goes you
see okay let's take maybe one or two
more
questions Malik said says when are doing
a when are you arranging a Meetup let's
do it Maharashtra let's see I haven't
thought about it but one could do it in
the future for sure I will let you guys
know
uh okay let's take one or two more
questions
broker inside says people who say that
Indian genetics are weak Etc need to
realize that a civilization that is so
old and ancient and still surv surviving
for that it's impossible to have weak
genetics I agree yeah it's not the
Indian genetics that's weak it's that
Indian kids they have to focus so much
on education that they can't even go and
have a nice run outside okay and the
Indian diet is the tradition starvation
diet of the past two and a half
centuries which we were forced to adopt
because of the starvation imposed Upon
Us by the British and so on so that's
why once these things change we will
become very different physically we
already doing very well in sports we are
beginning to do really well in sports in
a few years everything's going to change
so I agree with you genetics there's no
issue with us genetically we're
genetically wonderful when I was a kid
people used to say Indians can't Bowl
fast Indians can't produce fast Bowlers
today India has the best fast Bowlers in
the
world India went to Australia twice on
two tours and and defeated Australia
with our fast bowling strength so we
have the best fast Bowlers in the world
so this entire nonsense about Indians
having bad genetics once again I will
attribute to India's rotten education
system that Indians still believe this
it's so easy to make Indians believe all
kinds of
nonsense
right
okay sesh Gupta says despite learning
from this garbage education system how
did respected apj Abdul Kalam and
scientists of ISRO come up with
excellent learning outcomes how did they
get practical knowledge through
self-study there is no shortage of genus
level talent in
India shras Raman is a great example he
was almost destroyed by the education
system he used to get the best the
highest marks in maths and he used to
fail in all other subjects so why didn't
his teachers identify him as a genius in
mathematics and and stop forcing him to
sit for exams in other subjects just
focus on math but the education system
says no no no you have to get good math
and everything so this almost destroyed
that guy's career ramanujan so we have
no shortage of Genius level talent in
India and the ones who succeed succeed
despite the education system not because
of the education system they spent time
alone on their own studying what
interests them on top of all the
nonsense homework and classwork you to
do and that's how they acquire real
knowledge because they're passionate
about something and they will do extra
work additional work on top of all the
other work they already have to do
that's how they succeed there are so
many students who are so hardworking in
India and who are so incredibly
brilliant and that's that's how they
succeed not because of the education
system despite the education
system okay let's take one last
question one last
question red says how did the original
Egyptian culture and religion die out is
there anything left of the Original
Egyptian culture nothing only the
buildings the pyramids it all began
with well there was the there were the
sea peoples who came and kind of did
some dents to Egypt's strength the hixus
who who could have been Indo Indo Arian
origin people perhaps also occupied
Egypt for a century and a half but that
was okay Egypt recovered from that then
I think in the 3D Century BC Egypt was
under Persian occupation
okay and the Egyptians when Alexander
came they saw him as a great
Liberator but then they realized the
persans were way better than the the
Greeks so Egypt's downfall begins with
the Greek occupation of
Egypt which began when the Egyptians
allowed Alexander to walk into Egypt
they thought it was a great Savior for
them who would get rid of the Persians
yeah he got rid of the Persians but he
destroyed Egypt he and his
uh political descendants destroyed Egypt
that they started the process of
destroying Egypt's
culture so the Persians were actually
good not the Greeks so then you had the
toid toic toic Dynasty in Egypt which
was the dynasty installed by Alexander
the first governor he installed was toy
something toy the first and then you had
his descendants who were ruling Egypt
Cleopatra was Greek she was not Egyptian
she was not a black lady she was a white
lady or brown lady whatever Greek Lady
light brown so then so you had that the
Greek influence on on Egypt so that
starts the process then Julius Caesar
conquers
Egypt okay and he discovers the Greeks
are ruling Egypt he enough now it'll be
Romans who who rule Egypt so then this
Roman rule over Egypt the so that that
brings in more changes and then it all
ends with the Arabic conquest of Egypt
which entirely ends everything that is
Egyptian in nature in Egypt today the
people of Egypt consider themselves to
be Arabic to be Arabs they speak the
Arabic language and Egyptian flavored
Arabic language and there is no Original
Egyptian vocabulary left in the language
there's no Egyptian culture culture or
Customs left it's just an extension of
the Arabic World there is nothing left
of the Original Egyptian culture in
practice in Egypt today
okay do we have anything else
interesting
uh okay Dr J Shankar says why are we not
friends with North Korea well I'll tell
you what we aren't enemies with North
Korea we have diplomatic relations with
them and uh we have reasonably good
cordial relations with North Korea so I
would not say that we are not friends we
certainly are not enemies we don't have
bad relations with North Korea we have
reasonably good relations with North
Korea and as an Indian citizen you can
even travel to North Korea it it'll cost
you money because you don't get it's
very hard to reach there but it's
possible and if you wear an Indian dress
over there you're going to be treated
treated really well okay so I would say
that we have reasonably good relations
with North Korea and if it were not for
for the pressures that come from the
west from the US we may perhaps even
have better relations with North Korea
but the reason there are multiple layers
of complexity North Korea is a Chinese
satellite and Chinese vasal it's uh so
all that complicates matters but overall
I would not say that we are not friends
I I would say that we have reasonably
good relations with North
Korea okay with that I'm going to end
this session we have once again crossed
a million U what am I saying two hours
I saw
this comment strangely proton is saying
you are reaching 1 million Subs any
party I guess we'll have an online party
that's all I can do for you because
otherwise how how do I invite a million
people yeah eventually it'll happen soon
enough I suppose so it is all thanks to
you that will happen and I am incredibly
genuinely very very grateful for your
viewership I had never imagined that I
would have I would be reaching a million
subscribers someday on YouTube so yeah
it's all thanks to you that it will
happen thank you very much all right
with that let me end today's session
once again thank you everyone for
watching for all your questions and
apologies to those of you whose
questions I could not take but I have
more live streams coming up very soon
and hopefully I will take your questions
on that thank you so much and I will see
you in the next one take care and keep
raising your standards bye